Finding Aid for the Elizabeth Case Papers, 1930-2006
Elmira College
Finding Aid for the Elizabeth Case Papers, 1930-2006
The bulk of the collection is comprised of the multidisciplinary works of Elizabeth Case. Paintings, illustrations, sketches, animation, poetry, spoken word and written works are the artistic disciplines represented in the collection. The personal papers of Elizabeth Case are at a minimum; however, a compilation of editorials, personal photographs and photograph slides from exhibitions as well as certificates of her lifetime achievements provide a unique perspective of the artist.
6.33 linear ft. (9 boxes, 77 paintings)
Case, Elizabeth
Elmira College Archives, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, N.Y.
Unrestricted
Elizabeth Case was born in Long Beach, California to parents Nelson Case II, a beloved radio announcer, and Sarah Lee Odend’hal. Case attended Elmira College, the French Institute, and the Art Student’s League.
Case became one of the first female animation artists for Walt Disney in 1956 at the age of 26. She worked as an animator on the Walt Disney classic, Sleeping Beauty. After being laid off at the completion of the film, Case walked away from animation. By the age of 29, Case was writing and reading poetry in San Francisco where she was known as “Mother of the Beat Generation.”
In another career turn, Case was hired as the U.S. Navy Combat Artist. Later she would forge a career as a muralist, completing projects for the Church of the Good Shepard in Fort Lee, New Jersey, the Los Angeles County Hospital, and the New Jersey Public Library.
Case served on the Board of Directors of the National Society of Mural Painters. While on the board, Case wrote the mural handbook and published several articles in major art periodicals. She received many distinction for her life’s work including “Who’s Who in America,” ”Who’s Who of American Women,” “Who’s Who in American Art,” and “Who’s Who in the Cast;” along with several achievement and appreciation certificates from Elmira College.
Elizabeth Case died in 2006 at the age of 76.
Case, Elizabeth; Painters—United States—20th Century; Poets; Illustrators; Women artists; Painting; slides (photographs); phonograph records; compact discs; notebooks; editorials; correspondence
The collection is comprised of two major components: the art of Elizabeth Case containing paintings, illustrations, animations, sketches, poetry, spoken word and written works, and photographs (photographic slides) of Case’s artwork, exhibitions and personal photographs.
The collection contains 77 paintings and sketches including numerous other journals and binders. The journals are comprised of notes, short stories, poems, and rough sketches. A spoken word phonograph record and compact disc of her narration of two original poems, “Pax” and “Dig” as well as a collection titled, “Zero to Sixty in 15 minutes” from 2001 are highlights of the collection.
The collection contains binders with programs, newspaper articles, and correspondence about her exhibitions. The majority of the photographs and photograph slides are of her artwork, murals and photographs from exhibitions.
The collection primarily documents the creative life and output of Elizabeth Case. Documents about the artist’s personal life are at a minimum.
ORGANIZATIONAL NOTE:
The Elizabeth Case Collection has been organized into the following Series:
Series 1: Personal Papers [1958-2006, Undated]
Series 2: Sketches and Illustrations [1948, Undated]
Series 3: Art Media Projects [1965-1969, Undated]
Series 4: Photographs
Sub-Series 1: Personal Photographs
Sub-Series 2: Exhibitions, Artwork, and Murals
Series 5: Photographic Slides
Series 6: Certificates and Awards
Series 7: Paintings
- SERIES 1: PERSONAL PAPERS [1958-2006, undated], The series contains journals, art records, correspondence, and editorials. This series is in loose chronological order.
  - Journals – Two journals, includes notes and some rough sketches [undated], 1958-2006 (Box-folder 1 1)
  - Journal -- Includes Short Stories, notes, rough sketches [1958] (Box-folder 1 2)
  - Journal -- Includes notes, comments, thoughts, some rough sketches [Late 1960s-1979] (Box-folder 1 3)
  - Scrapbook -- Contains drawings by Ginxi, [1954, undated] (In Oversize Box) (Box-folder 1 4)
  - Art Records -- Includes newspaper articles, promotional materials, biographies, resume, statements, notes [1984-1999] (Box-folder 1 5)
  - Correspondence [1984-2006] (Box-folder 1 6)
  - "Zero to Sixty in Fifteen Minutes" -- A collection of editorials [1999-2001, Undated] (Box-folder 1 7)
  - "The Wrong Elf" Story -- Incomplete autobiography, pages 3-9 of 16 [2000's?] (Box-folder 1 8)
  - Classes Taught by Case -- Includes registration forms, supplies list, lesson examples [2002-2004] (Box-folder 1 9)
  - Newspaper Article [2003] (Framed—In Oversize Box) (Box-folder 1 10)
  - Notes and Paperwork -- Includes will, death certificate, funeral information, plans [2006] (Box-folder 1 11)
  - Lock of Case's Hair [undated] (Box-folder 1 12)
  - United States Coast Guard Auxiliary Challenger Coin (2) [undated] (Box-folder 1 13)
- SERIES 2: SKETCHES AND ILLUSTRATIONS [1948, undated], This series contains sketches, illustrations, and animation designs by Case. Most artifacts were left in original order.
  - Animation for Red Tree -- Includes Illustrations [undated] (Box-folder 2 1)
  - Illustrations of Gnomes with Titles [undated] (Box-folder 2 2)
  - Sketchbook -- Includes Rough Sketches, Drawings [undated] (Box-folder 2 3)
  - Sketchbook -- Includes Rough Sketches [1948] (Box-folder 2 4)
  - Sketch -- Includes Framed Sketch [undated] (Box-folder 2 5)
  - Sketches (2) [undated] (Sketches in Oversize) (Box-folder 2 6)
- SERIES 3: ART MEDIA PROJECTS [1965-1969, undated], This series contains books, cassettes, microfilm, phonographs, reel-to-reel and a floppy disk. This series is arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Book: "Walt Disney's Story of Sleeping Beauty with Songs from the Film" -- Illustrated by Case [1965] (Box-folder 3 1)
  - Cassette: "Sample My Voice” [Undated] (Box-folder 3 2)
  - Microfilm: Pencil Test [Undated] (In Oversize) (Box-folder 3 3)
  - Phonograph Record: "Pax and Dig" -- Includes CD, 8 copies [1969] (Box-folder 3 4)
  - Reel to Reel -- "Pax and Dig," Includes Original Recordings, Certificate of Registration to Copyright, Correspondence [1969] (Box-folder 3 5)
  - Reel to Reel (3) [Undated] (Not sure if they are Related to "Pax and Dig") (Box-folder 3 6)
  - 3 1/2 inch Floppy Disk -- Not Titled [Undated] (Box-folder 3 7)
- SERIES 4: PHOTOGRAPHS [1930-2001, undated]
  - SUB-SERIES 1: PERSONAL PHOTOGRAPHS [1930-2001, undated], This series contains photographs and negatives. This series includes photographs from her time serving as a Navy Combat Artist.
    - Photograph Album -- Album of Elizabeth Case's Mother, Ginxi Case Zwicker [1930-1952, undated] (4 1)
    - Navy Photographs [undated] (Box-folder 4 2)
    - Photographs and Negatives – “Family, Sue Hillard Undercliff, Pat, PTGs, Mural GTI, Pro Subjects, River, Op Soul '91 (?), Mamma, Sculpture" [undated] (Box-folder 4 3)
    - Negatives -- Cataloged [1936, Undated] (Book) (Box-folder 4 4)
    - Negatives -- "Mixed" (Personal) [1995-1999] (Box-folder 4 5)
    - Negatives -- "Xmas 2000", "Halloween 2K", "November 2K", "Dolls", "Feb or March? 2K", "Mini PTGs W/C PTGs Jan 2001" [2000-2001] (Box-folder 4 6)
  - SUB-SERIES 2: EXHIBITION, ARTWORK AND MURALS [1975-2001, undated], This series contains photos of Case’s exhibitions and artwork. This series is arranged in loose chronological order with the bulk of the sub-series have no known dates.
    - Exhibition "Scrapbook" -- Primarily photographs and slides with programs of Exhibitions [1975-2001] (Box-folder 5 1)
    - "Typography Aa to Z" and "Our Town" Exhibits -- Includes Photographs of Murals, Newspaper Articles, Information on Individual Murals [1991] (Box-folder 5 2)
    - Art Exhibit -- Includes Photographs of Paintings and Illustrations [undated] (Box-folder 5 3)
    - Photographs -- Miscellaneous with a Story [undated] (Box-folder 5 4)
    - Photographs of Murals with Descriptions [undated] (Box-folder 5 5)
    - Miscellaneous -- Photographs of Paintings, Elizabeth Case, Sculptures, Murals [undated] (Box-folder 5 6)
- SERIES 5: PHOTOGRAPHIC SLIDES [1969-2003, undated], This Series contain slides of Case’s artwork and personal life. Slides are in individual plastic protectors. Slide boxes have retained their original titles. This series is arranged by container type.
  - Artwork Binder -- Miscellaneous [1975-2003, undated] (Box-folder 6 1)
  - Artwork Binder -- Tabs for Faces, Water (Navy), Drawings in Work, Old-Odd, Jungle, Portrait [1967-1994] (Box-folder 6 2)
  - Artwork Binder -- Miscellaneous [1984-1996] (Box-folder 6 3)
  - Artwork Binder -- Artwork, Personal, Photographs, Newspaper Articles [1979-1994] (6 4)
  - Artwork Binder -- "Commercial", "Murals", Notes [1974-1983] (Box-folder 6 5)
  - Artwork Binder -- Includes four photographs of artwork [1978-1984] (Box-folder 6 6)
  - Slide boxes -- Original box titles, "Scenery Subj.", "Avalible PTGs", "OP Sail Backyard", "All Good Paintings", "Mural and A-Z", "PTG Dupes" [1976-1995, undated] (Box-folder 7 1)
  - Slide boxes -- Original box titles, "Edgewater", "PTGs People", "USS Ling Sub and Memorial Services", Miscellaneous Art [1998-2001] (Box-folder 7 1)
  - Slide boxes -- Original box titles, "Veggie", "Good PTGs", "Xmas Toys, Cats" [1978-1997, undated] (Box-folder 7 1)
  - Slide boxes -- Original box titles, "Water Color PTGs", "Paintings", "Commercial" [1994-2002] (Box-folder 7 1)
  - Slide box -- Miscellaneous: Personal, Exhibition, Paintings [1969-1994] (Box-folder 8 1)
- SERIES 6: CERTIFICATES AND AWARDS [1974-1982], This series contains various certificates and Awards including two of her “Who’s Who” awards: “Who’s Who of American Women” and “Who’s Who in the Cast.” Most certificates and awards have been removed from frames. The series has been arranged chronologically by date of issue.
  - Borough of Cliffside Park, N.Y. for Advancement of Cultural and Artistic Awareness [1974] (Box-folder 9 1)
  - Elmira College Certificate of Appreciation [1976] (Box-folder 9 2)
  - Borough of Edgewater, N.J. Certificate of Appreciation [1976] (Box-folder 9 3)
  - Elmira College Distinguished Achievement Award [1976] (Box-folder 9 4)
  - Who's Who of American Women [1979-1980] (Box-folder 9 5)
  - Who's Who in the Cast [1981-1982] (Box-folder 9 6)
- SERIES 7: PAINTINGS AND DRAWINGS, 1930-2006; This series contains primarily framed artworks and is arranged alphabetically by title of work.
  - Another Era, A Touch of Lavender [undated], 1930-2006
  - At the Top -- Abstracted view looking downward, Two adults with two children in foreground, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Backyard Game -- Two girls in a stream with bushes in the background under a blue sky, one girl with hula hoop over and around her head, the other with only her back in view, raising her left leg. Pastel on Paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Backyard Tree -- Tree with the door and window to brick house behind. Charcoal and pastel [1973?]
  - Be a Clown; Jester -- Bust portrait of clown with red hat, looking at hands held out below his face, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Beginner -- full figure of a young ballerina with long blonde hair, looking left, with right leg raised [undated], 1930-2006
  - Blue River, Sky and Bridge [undated], 1930-2006
  - Boy and Girl -- Boy and girl back to back with house in background, pen and ink and watercolor [undated], 1930-2006
  - But I Like to Wear Women's Clothes -- Sketch of a women. Pen and Ink [undated], 1930-2006
  - Child Crying -- Full length Portrait of a girl sitting against a tree with her left arm covering her face. Oil on Canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Dancer #1 -- 1 in series of 5. Full body portrait of a dancer, arms folded behind her head, red checkered shirt around waist and red checkered band around head. Pencil/Colored pencil [undated], 1930-2006
  - Disneyland Carousel -- Semi-Abstract portrait of boy on white horse carousel [2002]
  - Distant View of Denver -- Written on front: “July 2000 - view of Colorado Mountians Coming into Denver from Amtrak’s Zephyr Westbound.” On back: “Watercolor seen and painted on the train Amtrak’s Zephyr heading West." Watercolor [2000]
  - Do You Believe -- Cross with words, “He is Dead, Born of Woman, Son of God,” with three shrouded figures and one holding his face in his hands, Oil on Panel [undated], 1930-2006
  - Doll in the Grass -- Pen and Ink [1977]
  - Edna's Quilt -- Still life with candlestick, sunflower and statue of a woman sitting on a quilt [undated], 1930-2006
  - Face of a Girl -- Full face, bust portrait of a blonde haired woman. Oil on Canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - The Fight -- Fist in center of frame with hand reaching out to grab it in foreground and a face obscured by upraised hands in the background. Oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - French Doll -- Three-quarter length portrait of doll, watercolor [undated], 1930-2006
  - Friend's Play -- Two children sitting on beach with beach chairs behind them, girl holding sunglasses out to boy that is filling up a bucket with sand. Watercolor [2003]
  - Get Thee to a Nunnery [undated], 1930-2006
  - Girl and Flowers -- Bust portrait of women with flowered sash and flowers in hair, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - History of Women Voting (1st Panel) -- Half body portrait of a woman sitting behind a sleeping baby. Charcoal on brown paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - History of Women Voting (2nd Panel) -- Woman holding toddler, bust portrait of a woman in lower portion of page. Charcoal on brown paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - History of Women Voting (Triptych) [undated], 1930-2006
  - Holy Family -- Three figures standing in front of a door to a church. Oil on Canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Ishmael -- Bust portrait of man looking right, signed lower left, Elizabeth Case ‘94, Ishmael written lower right, oil [undated], 1930-2006
  - Janet -- Bust portrait of woman with red hair and yellow collared shirt, slightly left profile. Pastel on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Keith at Six -- Full-faced, half-length portrait of a body. Watercolor on paper [1960], 1930
  - Kids Wading -- Two boys on beach wearing yellow swimsuits, one boy with bucket in hand, watercolor on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Leaning Shed -- Dilapidated building, trees behind, with a single dead tree standing in front. Watercolor on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Madonna -- Bust portrait of woman at window with hands raised into frame, tree in window behind her. Oil on panel [undated], 1930-2006
  - Man, Woman and Child --Abstracted forms of a man with a woman holding a child. Oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Mixed Media: The Brushes you Need -- Three hands holding painting brushes for different media: watercolor, oil and acrylic; each brush has a streak of color, watercolor, oil, acrylic, 1930-2006
  - Night Fire Across the River -- View of a fire in along a city skyline from across the water, with trees obscuring view; in foreground, a bird bath to the left, stump of tree with teddy bear in center and a fire hydrant to the right. Oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Night Snow on the Hudson -- Night view of city lights from a hilltop looking down on rooftops, the hudson river and lights in the distance, pastel on paper, 1930-2006
  - Red Window -- Sketch of building with five detailed windows on second level of building, furthest window to left is lit with red light and a shadow of a figure can be seen in the window. Pencil and color pencil on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Root Stump -- Label on the back of the frame says: “The Stump was Bigger Than the Tree. Pen and Ink. Back when people were writing on their drawings, I did too.” Pen and ink [undated], 1930-2006
  - School's Out -- Group of pan fish in a slightly abstracted water setting [2003]
  - Self Portrait -- Pencil sketch of a hand drawing a face on a sheet of paper, left hand is holding the sheet [1972]
  - Self Portrait at 42 -- Bust portrait facing slightly right, window and curtain in background with a tree and a dim blue sky beyond, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Sitting Place -- Wooden chair with orange cushion facing slightly right, lamp with red shade behind and to the right in front of a window with half drawn beige blinds. Watercolor [undated], 1930-2006
  - Snug Harbor, Christmas on River Road -- View from porch deck, Santa dangling from chest down from roof, wintry backdrop. Watercolor on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - So, We're Miserable -- Now, What'll We Do? -- Boy and Girl back to Back. Pen and Ink [undated], 1930-2006
  - Study of Debi -- Portrait of a woman facing slightly right, looking up from a book. Oil on Canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Sweet Conversations -- Woman and a boy sitting on a bench in a park eating, numerous trees without foilage and apartment complexes beyond, a light blue sky above, gouache [undated], 1930-2006
  - Thaw -- View looking out window with doll and plant in the foreground and bare trees and bird bath beyond. Pastel on paper (water damaged) [undated], 1930-2006
  - The Tall Ships -- People in foreground with a river with boats and cityscape behind, gouache [undated], 1930-2006
  - Tent City -- Close up of a flowering pot, with numerous small homes (perhaps tents) in the background, blue sky. Watercolor, 1930-2006
  - Tony -- three quarter portrait of boy facing left, wearing cape, holding book in left hand and right hand resting on a swivel chair. Oil on panel [undated], 1930-2006
  - Toy Collage -- toys on a shelf, watercolor [undated], 1930-2006
  - Two to Get Ready -- Back has a note that also calls this “Ready to Go” and “Hat and Scarves.” Oil on Canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Boy in Tree) -- Boy standing on the limbs of an apple tree, another figure to the left, abstract surroundings, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Box, Butterfly and Flowers) -- Open red box filled with flowers and butterfly on top of flowers. Watercolor [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Buffalo Sketch) -- head sketch of a buffalo, charcoal on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Charcoal abstract) -- Charcoal on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Charcoal abstract) -- with hints of purple, charcoal on paper [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Children at the Circus) -- Two children, boy at left with kite at his side, girl at right with left hand raised, clown in background at right edge. Oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Children Playing in Pond) -- Two kids playing in fountain with dolls, cat in the right and left foreground, trees with cross behind and to the right, water and city skyline to the left. Oil on panel [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Clown) -- Half-length portrait of a clown, looking to the left,right hand in white polka dot glove in a waving motion, Oil on Canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Girl and Boy playing frisbee) -- Oil on Canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Girl Holding Cross by Window) -- Egg Tempera on Panel [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Red Figures) -- Red figures walking towards a tear in the sky, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Vase) -- Semi-Abstract vase and flowers, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Untitled (Woods and Flowers) -- Yard with tree greenery and red and pink flowers, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Veggie Tree -- animated vegetable pyramid, print [undated], 1930-2006
  - View Through the Trees -- Green foliage around edge of frame, water with cityscape beyond, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Wading Pond --Cityscape with building and powerlines in view, foreground full of people with fountain beyond with bodies wading in the water. Pastel on paper [1979]
  - Waiting for the Circus Train -- Two boys looking left in foreground with road of circus performers entering from left to right and receding into the distance, a farmhouse if out beyond, last glimpse of light on the horizon to the right. Oil on panel [undated], 1930-2006
  - Wally -- Half length portrait of a freckle faced boy with striped shirt, right hand clasping left arm on table, profile slightly left. Oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Whitesbog Shed -- Dilapidated barn with two small trees in the foreground, tree to the left and trees behind, blue sky in the upper right, watercolor [undated], 1930-2006
  - Why Am I Here? -- Baby in a nest full of baby birds. Pen and Ink [1955]
  - Woman in a Hat -- portrait, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Young Love -- Semi-abstract painting, bust of two figures, one full face, the other facing left, with abstract surroundings, oil on canvas [undated], 1930-2006
  - Young Maya Angelou -- portrait [undated], 1930-2006